A Finding Aid to the Clay Spohn Papers, circa 1862-1985, bulk 1890-1985, in the Archives of American Art
Archives of American Art
- Clay Spohn Papers, circa 1862-1985, undated; Series 2; Archival Resource Key; (boxes 1-22, OV 23, 19.9 linear ft.)
  - Correspondence, 1925-1981, undated; 2.2; Archival Resource Key; (boxes 2-5, 4.7 linear feet)
    Tirana, Rosamond: undated and 1958-1962 (10 letters); see Corbett, Edward for additional letters
    Van Duren, Allan and Betsy: 1953 (1 letter)
    Van Ingen, Pat: 1973 (2 letters)
    Varda, Yantoo?: 1949 (1 letter)
    Visual Arts Gallery: 1967 (2 letters)
    Vollmer, George A.: 1945-1948 (3 letters)
    Von Herberg, Charlotte: 1950-1958 (2 letters)
    Wakefield, Ruth Cravath: 1943 (1 letter of recommendation for Spohn)
    Wandell, Walt and Doreen: 1958 (1 letter)
    Wasley, Emily (aunt) and Sarah Rhoads (cousin): 1946-1955 (14 letters)
    Wehrer, Anne: 1974 (1 letter)
    Whaley, Bill: 1974 (1 letter)
    White, Minor: 1963 (1 letter)
    Who's Who In American Art: 1952-1969 (5 letters)
    Who's Who In The Midwest: 1959 (1 letter)
    Who's Who In The West: 1959 (1 letter)
    Willard, Charlotte: 1960-1967 (3 letters)
    Williams, Matilda A.: 1958 (1 letter)
    Wilmans, Margery and Steve: 1974 (1 letter)
    Winston, James W.: 1941 (1 letter)
    Wise: Howard Wise Gallery: 1962 (1 letter)
    Woelffer, Emerson and Diana: 1955-1958 (5 letters)
    Wood, Ralph: 1960-1970 (5 letters)
    Wright, Dorothy: 1926 (1 letter)
    Wurlitzer: Helene Wurlitzer Foundation: 1954-1957 (3 letters)
    Young-Hunter, Mrs. John: 1959 (1 letter)
    Correspondence is on reels 5461-5470.
    - Correspondence, 1925-May, 1953, undated; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 16-52)
      Scope and Contents
      Reel 5461
    - Correspondence, June, 1953-1955; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 53-71)
      Reel 5462
    - Correspondence, 1956-July 13-16, 1958; Archival Resource Key (Box 2, Folder 1-16)
    - Correspondence, July 13-16, 1958-June, 1963; Archival Resource Key (Box 2, Folder 17-58)
      Reel 5463
    - Correspondence, June, 1963-April-June, 1967; Archival Resource Key (Box 3, Folder 1-35)
      Reel 5464
    - Correspondence, April-June, 1967-October, 1969; Archival Resource Key (Box 3, Folder 36-57)
      Reel 5465
    - Correspondence, November, 1969-February 1-10, 1970; Archival Resource Key (Box 4, Folder 1-6)
    - Correspondence, February 1-10, 1970-April 21-30, 1971; Archival Resource Key (Box 4, Folder 7-30)
      Reel 5466
    - Correspondence, April 21-30, 1971-January 1-19, 1973; Archival Resource Key (Box 4, Folder 31-55)
      Reel 5467
    - Correspondence, Jan 1-19, 1973-March, 1973; Archival Resource Key (Box 4, Folder 56-59)
      Reel 5468
    - Correspondence, April, 1973-September, 21-30, 1974; Archival Resource Key (Box 5, Folder 1-18)
    - Correspondence, October, 1974-March-May, 1976; Archival Resource Key (Box 5, Folder 19-40)
      Reel 5469
    - Correspondence, June 3, 1976-1981; Archival Resource Key (Box 5, Folder 41-61)
      Reel 5470
  - Business Records, 1890-1983; 2.3; Archival Resource Key; (boxes 6-7, 1.6 linear feet)
    Business records primarily consist of Spohn's general accounting records, account books, banking records, contracts, inventories of artwork sold, records of support from the Lannan Foundation, records concerning Spohn's house in Taos, and miscellaneous receipts for healthcare, travel, art supplies, photographic services, and shipping. This subseries also includes documents concerning the companies managed by Spohn's father, John H. Spohn, and the patents and estate papers of Spohn's brother, John H. Spohn, Jr. These can be found at the beginning of the subseries.
    Business records are unfilmed.
    - John H. Spohn, 1890-1928; Archival Resource Key (Box 6, Folder 1)
    - John H. Spohn, Jr., 1940-1950; Archival Resource Key (Box 6, Folder 2-4)
    - General Accounts, 1950-1975; Archival Resource Key (Box 6, Folder 5-7)
    - Account Books, 1932-1976; Archival Resource Key; (18 books) (Box 6, Folder 8-25)
    - Banking Records, 1943-1977; Archival Resource Key (Box 6, Folder 26-53)
    - Contract and Financial Records (mural on Bob's Fine Food restaurant), 1945-1946; Archival Resource Key (Box 6, Folder 54)
    - Contract and Consignment Records for The Little Gallery, Taos, NM, 1957; Archival Resource Key (Box 6, Folder 55)
    - Inventory of Artwork in the Estate of Clay Spohn, 1981-1983; Archival Resource Key (Box 6, Folder 56)
    - Records of Artwork Sold, 1941-1970; Archival Resource Key (Box 6, Folder 57-59)
    - Records of Support from the Lannan Foundation, 1961-1962; Archival Resource Key (Box 7, Folder 1-6)
    - Records of Stocks, 1939-1969; Archival Resource Key (Box 7, Folder 7)
    - Insurance, 1973; Archival Resource Key (Box 7, Folder 8)
    - Spohn's House in Taos, 1952-1977; Archival Resource Key (Box 7, Folder 9-14)
    - Receipts, 1933-1978; Archival Resource Key (Box 7, Folder 15-24)
  - Notes and Writings, 1924-1985, undated; 2.4; Archival Resource Key; (boxes 7-18, 10.8 linear feet)
    This subseries contains miscellaneous notes and writings and includes 188 notebooks, address lists, a card file of book titles, Spohn's "Subject Location," "Index and Date," and "School of Visual Arts" files, and two typescripts by other writers. The miscellaneous notes and writings, and the notebooks, are concerned with various topics, often intermingled, such as teaching notes; lists of names, books, and groceries needed; financial records for art supplies; Spohn's thoughts on philosophy and art; dietary advice; annotated studies and calculations concerning the "trisection of an arbitrary angle"; notes for his unpublished literary work "The Book," (sometimes entitled "The Actual Book" or "The Truth Book"); and brief and incomplete drafts written either for writing class assignments or for "The Book."
    Files on the School of Visual Arts contains class schedules, grade sheets, and 37 notebooks of class assignments, records of student grades, notes for lectures, lists of books for teaching, writings about teaching, and notes on art supplies for class.
    Notes and writings are unfilmed unless noted otherwise.
    - Miscellaneous Notes and Writings, 1924-1985, undated; Archival Resource Key (Box 7, Folder 25-57)
    - Miscellaneous Notes and Writings, 1951-1958; Archival Resource Key (Box 8, Folder 1-56)
    - Miscellaneous Notes and Writings, 1959-June, 1962; Archival Resource Key (Box 9, Folder 1-57)
    - Miscellaneous Notes and Writings, July, 1962-May, 1970; Archival Resource Key (Box 10, Folder 1-62)
    - Miscellaneous Notes and Writings, June, 1970-1985; Archival Resource Key (Box 11, Folder 1-47)
    - Notebooks 1-21, 1926-1927; Archival Resource Key (Box 11, Folder 48-63)
    - Notebooks 22-76, 1927-1962; Archival Resource Key (Box 12, Folder 1-48)
    - Notebooks 77-105, 1962-1965; Archival Resource Key (Box 13, Folder 1-29)
    - Notebooks 106-136, 1965-1968; Archival Resource Key (Box 14, Folder 1-23)
    - Notebooks 137-163, 1968-1973; Archival Resource Key (Box 15, Folder 1-25)
    - Notebooks 164-182, 1973-1976; Archival Resource Key (Box 16, Folder 1-19)
    - Notebooks 183-188, 1976-1977; Archival Resource Key (Box 17, Folder 1-6)
    - Address Lists, undated; Archival Resource Key (Box 17, Folder 7)
    - Card File of Book Titles, 1959-1976; Archival Resource Key (Box 17, Folder 8-12)
    - Spohn's "Subject Location File", 1960-1961; Archival Resource Key (Box 17, Folder 13)
    - Spohn's "Index and Date File,", 1960-1961; Archival Resource Key (Box 17, Folder 14-19)
      Reel 5471
    - Notes from Private Trade School Teacher's Course at N.Y.U., 1965; Archival Resource Key (Box 17, Folder 20-22)
    - School of Visual Arts Notebook, 1964-1970; Archival Resource Key (Box 17, Folder 23-33)
    - School of Visual Arts Notebook, cont., 1964-1970; Archival Resource Key (Box 18, Folder 1-12)
    - Engagement Calendars, 1965, 1976; Archival Resource Key (Box 18, Folder 13-14)
    - Typescript, "The Sickness of American Culture" by Reinhold Niebuhr, undated; Archival Resource Key (Box 18, Folder 15)
    - Typescript, "Clay Spohn's Museum" by Douglas Macagy, 1965?; Archival Resource Key (Box 18, Folder 16)
  - Artwork, 1926-1968, undated; 2.5; Archival Resource Key; (boxes 18, 22, and OV 23, 0.6 linear feet)
    Artwork consists of 557 drawings, including 27 undated drawings of Washington D.C., and 14 sketchbooks.
    Artwork is on reel 5472.
    - Drawings (see also box 22 and OV 23), 1926-1968, undated; Archival Resource Key (Box 18, Folder 17-38)
    - Sketchbooks (see also box 22), 1925-1939; Archival Resource Key (Box 18, Folder 39-48)
    - Oversized Drawings, 1926-1968, undated; Archival Resource Key (Box 22, Folder 1)
    - Oversized Sketchbooks, 1925-1939; Archival Resource Key (Box 22, Folder 2)
    - Oversized Drawings, 1926-1968, undated; Archival Resource Key (Box OV 23)
  - Printed Material, 1894-1977, undated; 2.6; Archival Resource Key; (boxes 18-19, 1.5 linear feet)
    Printed material consists of clippings, exhibition announcements and catalogs for Spohn and others, exhibition prospectuses, reproductions of artwork, calendars of events, programs, brochures, books, and miscellaneous printed material.
    Printed materials are on reels 5472-5474.
    - Clippings, 1930-1939, undated; Archival Resource Key (Box 18, Folder 49-51)
    - Clippings, 1941-1963; Archival Resource Key (Box 18, Folder 52-68)
    - Clippings, 1964-1977; Archival Resource Key (Box 19, Folder 1-8)
    - Exhibition Announcements and Catalogs for Spohn, 1939-1977; Archival Resource Key (Box 19, Folder 9-12)
    - Exhibition Announcements and Catalogs for Others, 1940-1977; Archival Resource Key (Box 19, Folder 13-17)
    - Exhibition Prospectuses, 1945-1954; Archival Resource Key (Box 19, Folder 18)
    - Reproductions of Artwork, undated; Archival Resource Key (Box 19, Folder 19)
    - Calendars of events, 1965-1977; Archival Resource Key (Box 19, Folder 20)
    - Programs, 1965-1969; Archival Resource Key (Box 19, Folder 21)
    - Brochures Concerning Taos Artists, undated; Archival Resource Key (Box 19, Folder 22)
    - Brochures Concerning the School of Visual Arts, 1965-1969; Archival Resource Key (Box 19, Folder 23-24)
    - Brochures Concerning Miscellaneous Schools, 1949-1967; Archival Resource Key (Box 19, Folder 25)
    - Brochures Concerning the Oakland Museum, undated; Archival Resource Key (Box 19, Folder 26)
    - Brochures Concerning Art Supplies, 1956-1963; Archival Resource Key (Box 19, Folder 27-29)
    - Brochures Concerning Books, 1969, undated; Archival Resource Key (Box 19, Folder 30)
    - Brochures Concerning Health, 1958-1973; Archival Resource Key (Box 19, Folder 31-35)
    - Miscellaneous brochures, undated; Archival Resource Key (Box 19, Folder 36)
    - Book, Riverside Recipes, 1894; Archival Resource Key (Box 19, Folder 37)
    - Book, A Poet's Breath, by Judson Crews, 1950; Archival Resource Key (Box 19, Folder 38)
    - Book, Painting and Sculpture, Published by the San Francisco Art Association, 1952; Archival Resource Key (Box 19, Folder 39)
    - Book, Applied Teaching Techniques by Gilbert Weaver and Louis Cenci, 1960; Archival Resource Key (Box 19, Folder 40)
    - Miscellaneous Printed Material, 1940-1958; Archival Resource Key (Box 19, Folder 41)
  - Photographs, circa 1862-1977, undated; 2.7; Archival Resource Key; (boxes 20-22, 0.5 linear feet)
    Photographs are of Spohn and his family, colleagues, studio, house in Taos, exhibition installations, and artwork. There are also photographs of San Francisco, including six views of damage done by the 1906 earthquake. Colleagues pictured in the photographs include Marion Karnes, Urban Neininger, Jeanne Reynal, Louis Ribak, Alfred Rogoway, and Maurice Sievan.
    Photographs of artwork for projects by Spohn picture the following: an entrance hall mural for Officers Club, San Francisco (undated); a cartoon for copper repousee sculpture for Carmel, California, Volunteer Fire Department (1936); a cartoon for copper repousee sculpture for Castro Valley Community Center (1937); a mural for Montebello, California, post office (1938); and a mural for Los Gatos Union High School (1939).
    Photographs are on reel 5474.
    - Spohn with Family Members, 1900-circa 1915; Archival Resource Key (Box 20, Folder 1-2)
    - Clay Spohn (see also box 22), circa 1916-1974; Archival Resource Key (Box 20, Folder 3-6)
    - Family Members, Archival Resource Key (Box 20)
      - Spohn's Paternal Grandfather, [circa 1862]; Archival Resource Key; (ambrotype) (Box 20, Folder 7)
      - Spohn's Grandmother, undated; Archival Resource Key (Box 20, Folder 8)
      - Spohn's Mother (see also box 22), undated; Archival Resource Key (Box 20, Folder 9)
      - Spohn's Father, circa 1890-1920; Archival Resource Key; (including 7 tintypes) (Box 20, Folder 10-12)
      - Spohn's Parents, circa 1910s-1920s; Archival Resource Key (Box 20, Folder 13-14)
      - Spohn's Brother and Friends, circa 1910-1940; Archival Resource Key (Box 20, Folder 15-17)
    - Family Friends, circa 1910-1920s; Archival Resource Key (Box 20, Folder 18-20)
    - Bell Moose Convention, 1917; Archival Resource Key (Box 20, Folder 21)
    - Spohn's Colleagues, 1944-1974; Archival Resource Key (Box 20, Folder 22)
    - Spohn's Childhood Home, circa 1900; Archival Resource Key (Box 20, Folder 23-24)
    - San Francisco Earthquake Damage, 1906; Archival Resource Key (Box 20, Folder 25)
    - From World War I, 1917; Archival Resource Key (Box 21, Folder 1)
    - Views of San Francisco, 1932; Archival Resource Key (Box 21, Folder 2)
    - Miscellaneous Travel Photographs, undated; Archival Resource Key (Box 21, Folder 3-5)
    - Spohn's House in Taos, 1952-1970; Archival Resource Key (Box 21, Folder 6-8)
    - Spohn's studio, 1977; Archival Resource Key (Box 21, Folder 9)
    - Exhibition Installations, undated; Archival Resource Key (Box 21, Folder 10)
    - Miscellaneous Artworks by Spohn (see also box 22), 1936-1977; Archival Resource Key (Box 21, Folder 11-13)
    - Projects, Entrance Hall Mural for Officers Club, San Francisco, undated; Archival Resource Key (Box 21, Folder 14)
    - Projects, Cartoon for Copper Repousee Sculpture for Carmel, California, Volunteer Fire Department, 1936; Archival Resource Key (Box 21, Folder 15)
    - Projects, Cartoon for Copper Repousee Sculpture for Castro Valley Community Center, 1937; Archival Resource Key (Box 21, Folder 16)
    - Projects, Mural for Montebello, California, Post Office, 1938; Archival Resource Key (Box 21, Folder 17)
    - Projects, Mural for Los Gatos Union High School, 1939; Archival Resource Key (Box 21, Folder 18)
    - Photograph of a Painting Number 10 by Mark Rothko, undated; Archival Resource Key (Box 21, Folder 19)
    - Oversized Photographs of Spohn, Family, and Artwork, 1916-1977, undated; Archival Resource Key (Box 22, Folder 3)
  - Artifacts, undated; 2.8; Archival Resource Key; (box 21, 1 folder)
    Artifacts consist of four military pins from Marion Karnes.
    Artifacts are unfilmed.
    - Military pins from Marion Karnes, undated; Archival Resource Key (Box 21, Folder 20)
- Addition to the Clay Spohn Papers, 1958-1977; Series 3; Archival Resource Key; 0.4 Linear feet box 24
  The addition includes nine notebooks of notes and writings on art, class assignments, telephone calls and appointments, plans and procedures, an index for the history and location of paintings, and financial records.
  The addition is unfilmed.
  - Notebook, Thoughts on Art, 1958; Archival Resource Key (Box 24, Folder 1)
  - Notebook, Art Notes, 1958; Archival Resource Key (Box 24, Folder 2)
  - Notebook, Plan and Procedure for One's Work, 1963; Archival Resource Key (Box 24, Folder 3)
  - Notebook, Telephone Records, Appointments, and Notes, 1969; Archival Resource Key (Box 24, Folder 4)
  - Notebook, Notes for The Real Book, 1969; Archival Resource Key (Box 24, Folder 5)
  - Notebook, Personal Notes, 1974; Archival Resource Key (Box 24, Folder 6)
  - Notebook, Class Assignments, 1977; Archival Resource Key (Box 24, Folder 7)
  - Notebook, Index of History and Location of Paintings, 1964-1965; Archival Resource Key (Box 24, Folder 8)
  - Notebook, Financial Records, 1973-1975; Archival Resource Key (Box 24, Folder 9)